I want to give you a new perspective.
أريد إعطاءكم منظورًا جديدًا.
That sounds grandiose, and it is.
والتي تبدو مفخمة، وهي كذلك.
I left Ireland yesterday morning.
غادرت إيرلندا صباح البارحة.
I traveled from Dublin to New York
سافرت من دوبلين إلى نيويورك
independently.
بشكل مستقل.
But the design of an airport,
ولكن تصميم المطار،
plane and terminal
والطائرة والمحطة
offers little independence when you're 105 and a half centimeters tall.
يقدم استقلالية قليلة عندما يكون طولك 105 ونصف سنتيمتر
For Americans, that's 3' 5".
بالنسبة للأمريكيين، تصبح 3.5 إنش.
I was whisked through the airport by airline assistants in a wheelchair.
نقلني مساعدو شركة الخطوط الجوية عبر المطار على الكرسي المتحرك.
Now, I don't need to use a wheelchair,
الآن، أنا لا أحتاج لاستخدام كرسي متحرك،
but the design of an airport
ولكن تصميم المطار
and its lack of accessibility
وافتقاده لسهولة التوصيل
means that it's my only way to get through.
يعني أنه طريقتي الوحيدة للعبور.
With my carry-on bag between my feet,
مع حقيبتي المحمولة بين قدمي،
I was wheeled through security, preclearance
دُفعتُ عبر الأمن،
and I arrived at my boarding gate.
ووصلت إلى بوابة العبور.
I use the accessibility services in the airport
أستخدم عادة خدمات الوصول في المطار
because most of the terminal is just not designed with me in mind.
لأن أغلب المحطات لم تؤخذ حالتي بعين الاعتبار حين تصميمها.
Take security, for example.
خذ الأمن كمثال.
I'm not strong enough to lift my carry-on bag
أنا لست قوية كفاية لأنقل حقيبة ظهري
from the ground to the carousel.
من الأرض إلى حزام الأمتعة.
I stand at eye level with it.
أنا أقف بمستوى العين معه.
And those who work in that space for safety purposes cannot help me
وأولئك الذين يعملون بمجال الأمن لا يستطيعون مساعدتي
and cannot do it for me.
ولايمكن لهم أن يقوموا بذلك لأجلي.
Design inhibits my autonomy and my independence.
تصميم يكبت استقلاليتي وحريتي.
But traveling at this size, it isn't all bad.
ولكن الترحال بهذا الحجم، ليس سيئًا مطلقًا.
The leg room in economy is like business class.
المقاعد في حصة الاقتصاد هي مثلها في صف تجارة الأعمال.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I often forget that I'm a little person.
أنسى أحيانًا أنني شخص ضئيل الحجم.
It's the physical environment and society that remind me.
إنها البيئة الفيزيائية والمجتمع ما يذكرني بالأمر.
Using a public bathroom is an excruciating experience.
استعمال المراحيض العامة تجربة مؤلمة.
I walk into the cubicle
أمشي إلى الحجرة
but I can't reach the lock on the door.
لكنني لا أستطيع أن أصل إلى قفل الباب.
I'm creative and resilient.
أنا مبدعة ومرنة.
I look around and see if there's a bin that I can turn upside down.
أتلفت حولي وأبحث عن صندوق لأضعه رأسًا على عقب.
Is it safe?
هل هو آمن؟
Not really.
ليس حقَا.
Is it hygienic and sanitary?
هل هو صحي أو نظيف؟
Definitely not.
من المؤكد لا.
But the alternative is much worse.
ولكن البديل أكثر سوءًا.
If that doesn't work, I use my phone.
إذا لم يجدِ ذلك، أستعمل هاتفي.
It gives me an additional four- to six-inch reach,
فهو يعطيني من أربع إلى ستة إنشات إضافية،
and I try to jam the lock closed with my iPhone.
وأحاول أن أضغط على القفل المغلق بواسطة هاتفي الـ iPhone.
Now, I imagine that's not what Jony Ive had in mind when he designed the iPhone,
والآن، أتصور أن هذا لم يكن في بال "جوني إيف" عندما صمم الـiPhone،
but it works.
لكنه ينجح.
The alternative is that I approach a stranger.
البديل أن أقترب من غريب.
I apologize profusely
أعتذر بإفراط
and I ask them to stand guard outside my cubicle door.
وأطلب منهم أن يقفوا حراسًا خارج باب حجرتي.
They do
إنهم يفعلون ذلك
and I emerge grateful
وأنا أظهر الامتنان
but absolutely mortified,
لكن بذُل بالطبع،
and hope that they didn't notice
وآمل أنهم لم يلاحظوا
that I left the bathroom without washing my hands.
أنني غادرت المرحاض بدون أن أغسل يدي.
I carry hand sanitizer with me every single day
أحمل معقم أيدي معي كل يوم
because the sink, soap dispenser, hand dryer and mirror
لأن المغسلة والصابون ومجفف الأيدي والمرآة
are all out of my reach.
كلها بعيدة عن متناولي.
Now, the accessible bathroom is somewhat of an option.
الآن، المرحاض سهل الوصول يمثل حلًا بعض الشيء.
In this space, I can reach the lock on the door,
في هذا المكان، أستطيع الوصول لقفل الباب،
the sink, the soap dispenser, the hand dryer and the mirror.
والمغسلة والصابون ومجفف الأيدي وللمرآة.
Yet, I cannot use the toilet.
حتى الآن لا أستطيع استخدام المرحاض.
It is deliberately designed higher
فهو مصمم بتعمد ليكون أعلى
so that wheelchair users can transfer across with ease.
كي يستطيع مستخدمو الكرسي المتحرك الانتقال إليه بسهولة.
This is a wonderful and necessary innovation,
هذا ابتكار رائع وضروري،
but in the design world, when we describe a new project or idea as accessible,
ولكن في التصميم العالمي، عندما نصف مشروع أو فكرة جديدة بأنها قابلة للوصول،
what does that mean?
ماذا يعني ذلك؟
Who is it accessible to?
إلى من هو قابل للوصول؟
And whose needs are not being accommodated for?
ومن هو الذي احتياجاته غير مجهز لها؟
Now, the bathroom is an example
الآن، غرفة المرحاض مثال
of where design impinges upon my dignity,
حيث التصميم يمس كرامتي،
but the physical environment impacts upon me in much more casual ways too,
ولكن البيئة الفيزيائية تؤثر علي بأكثر الطرق اعتيادية أيضًا،
something as simple as ordering a cup of coffee.
شيء ببساطة طلب كوب من القهوة.
Now, I'll admit it.
الآن، سأعترف بذلك.
I drink far too much coffee.
أنا أشرب الكثير من القهوة.
My order is a skinny vanilla latte,
طلبي هو فانيلا لاتيه خفيف،
but I'm trying to wean myself off the syrup.
لكنني أحاول أن أقطع عادتي عن الشرب.
But the coffee shop, it's not designed well,
لكن مقهى القهوة، ليس مصممًا جيدًا،
at least not for me.
على الأقل ليس بالنسبة لي.
Queuing, I'm standing beside the pastry cabinet
في الطابور، أقف بجانب كشك الحلويات
and the barista calls for the next order.
وتنادي النادلة الطلب التالي.
"Next, please!" they shout.
"التالي، من فضلك!" هم يصرخون.
They can't see me.
لا يمكنهم رؤيتي.
The person next to me in the queue points to my existence
الشخص التالي في الطابور يشير إلى وجودي
and everyone is embarrassed.
والكل محرج.
I order as quick as I can and I move along to collect my coffee.
أطلب بأسرع ما أستطيع وأذهب لإحضار قهوتي.
Now, think just for a second.
الآن، فكر فقط للحظة.
Where do they put it?
أين وضعوها؟
Up high and without a lid.
في الأعلى وبدون غطاء.
Reaching up to collect a coffee that I have paid for
الوصول للأعلى لجلب قهوتي التي دفعت ثمنها
is an incredibly dangerous experience.
هو تجربة خطرة بشكل لا يصدق.
But design also impinges on the clothes that I want to wear.
لكن التصميم يؤثر أيضًا على الملابس التي أريد ارتداءها.
I want garments that reflect my personality.
أريد ملابساً تعكس شخصيتي.
It's difficult to find in the childrenswear department.
إنه من الصعب العثور على ذلك في قسم ملابس الأطفال.
And often womenswear requires far too many alterations.
وغالبًا ما تتطلب الملابس النسائية العديد من البدائل.
I want shoes that affect my maturity, professionalism and sophistication.
أريد الأحذية التي تؤثر على نضجي، والاحترافية والأناقة.
Instead, I'm offered sneakers with Velcro straps and light-up shoes.
بدلًا من ذلك، يُعرض علي أحذية رياضية مع أشرطة وأحذية بضوء.
Now, I'm not totally opposed to light-up shoes.
الآن، أنا لست معارضة تمامًا لأحذية الضوء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But design also impacts on such simple things,
ولكن التصميم يؤثر على العديد من الأشياء البسيطة،
like sitting on a chair.
مثل الجلوس على الكرسي.
I cannot go from a standing to a seating position with grace.
لايمكنني الانتقال من وضعية الوقوف إلى الجلوس بارتياح.
Due to the standards of design heights of chairs,
بسبب تصميم الكرسي المرتفع،
I have to crawl on my hands and knees
علي أن أزحف على يدي وركبي
just to get on top of it,
لمجرد أن أصل لأعلاه،
whilst also being conscious that it might tip over at any stage.
بينما أكون مدركة بأنه من الممكن أن ينقلب في أي مرحلة.
But whilst design impacts on me
ولكن بيما يؤثر التصميم علي
whether it's a chair, a bathroom, a coffee shop, or clothes,
سواء كان كرسيًا أو مرحاضًا أو كوب قهوة أو ملابسًا،
I rely on and benefit
أنا أعتمد وأستفيد
from the kindness of strangers.
من لطافة الغرباء.
But not everybody is so nice.
ولكن ليس الجميع ودودًا.
I'm reminded that I'm a little person
أنا أُذكّر بأنني شخص ضئيل الحجم
when a stranger points,
عندما يشير الغريب،
stares,
يحدق،
laughs,
يضحك،
calls me a name,
يدعوني باسم،
or takes a photograph of me.
أو يأخذ صورة تذكارية لي.
This happens almost every day.
هذا يحدث غالبًا كل يوم.
With the rise of social media, it has given me an opportunity
مع صعود وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي، هذا يعطيني فرصة
and a platform to have a voice as a blogger and as an activist,
ومنصة ليكون لي صوت كمدونة وكناشطة،
but it has also made me nervous
ولكن هذا يجعلني أيضًا متوترة
that I might become a meme
بأنه من الممكن بأن أصبح "نمط"
or a viral sensation,
أو نبأ منتشر جدًا،
all without my consent.
كل هذا بدون سكوتي.
So let's take a moment right now
لذا دعونا نتوقف للحظة الآن
to make something very clear.
لتوضيح شيء ما.
The word "midget" is a slur.
الكلمة "قزم" هي إهانة.
It evolved from PT Barnum's era of circuses and freak shows.
تطورت منذ عهد "بارنوم" للسيرك والعروض الغريبة.
Society has evolved.
تطوّر المجتمع.
So should our vocabulary.
كذلك يجب على مفرداتنا.
Language is a powerful tool.
اللغة هي أداة قوية.
It does not just name our society.
هي ليست تعطي فقط لمجتمعنا اسمًا.
It shapes it.
هي تشكله.
I am incredibly proud to be a little person,
أنا فخورة بشكل لا يصدق لكوني شخص ضئيل،
to have inherited the condition of achondroplasia.
لأرث حالة "أكوندروبلاسيا".
But I am most proud to be Sinead.
ولكنني فخورة أكثر لكوني "سنياد".
Achondroplasia is the most common form of dwarfism.
أكوندروبلاسيا هو أكثر الحالات شيوعًا من التقزم.
Achondroplasia translates as "without cartilage formation."
أكوندروبلاسيا تترجم "دون تشكل الغضاريف."
I have short limbs and achondroplastic facial features,
لدي أطراف قصيرة وملامح وجه أوكندروبلاستية،
my forehead and my nose.
جبهتي وأنفي.
My arms do not straighten fully,
ذراعاي لا تستقيمان بشكل كامل،
but I can lick my elbow.
لكنني أستطيع لعق كوعي.
I'm not showing you that one.
أنا لا أعرض لكم ذلك.
Achondroplasia occurs in approximately one in every 20,000 births.
أكوندروبلاسيا يظهر لدى شخص من بين 20،000 مولود تقريبًا.
80 percent of little people are born to two average-height parents.
80 بالمئة من قصار القامة يولدون لأبوين معتدلي القامة.
That means that anybody in this room could have a child with achondroplasia.
هذا يعني أن أي شخص في هذه الغرفة يمكن أن يحصل على طفل مصاب بأكوندروبلاسيا.
Yet, I inherited my condition from my dad.
نعم، أنا ورثت حالتي من أبي.
I'd like to show you a photo of my family.
أود أن أريكم صورة لعائلتي.
My mother is average height,
أمي معتدلة الطول،
my father is a little person
أبي قصير القامة
and I am the eldest of five children.
وأنا الكبيرة بين الأبناء الخمسة.
I have three sisters and one brother.
لدي ثلاثة أخوات وأخ واحد.
They are all average height.
جميعهم معتدلي الطول.
I am incredibly fortunate to have been born into a family
أنا ممتنة بشكل لا يصدق لأنني ولدت في عائلة
that cultivated my curiosity and my tenacity,
تصقل فضولي ومثابرتي،
that protected me from the unkindness and ignorance of strangers
التي تحميني من عدم لطف الغرباء وجهلهم
and that armed me with the resilience, creativity and confidence
والتي تسلحني بالصمود والإبداع والثقة
that I needed to survive and manipulate the physical environment and society.
التي احتاجها لأنجو ولأتعامل مع البيئة الفيزيائية والمجتمع.
If I was to pinpoint any reason why I am successful,
إذا كان علي أن أحدد بدقة أي سبب لكوني ناجحة،
it is because I was and I am a loved child,
هذا لأنني كنت ومازلت طفلًا محبوبًا،
now, a loved child with a lot of sass and sarcasm,
الآن، طفل محبوب مع الكثير من السخرية والتهكم،
but a loved child nonetheless.
ولكن مع ذلك طفل محبوب.
In giving you an insight into who I am today
لإعطائكم تبصرة فيما أنا عليه اليوم
I wanted to offer you a new perspective.
أردت أن أعرض عليكم منظورًا جديدًا.
I wanted to challenge the idea
أردت أن أتحدى الفكرة
that design is but a tool to create function and beauty.
بأن التصميم هو مجرد أداة لصنع الأداء والجمال.
Design greatly impacts upon people's lives,
التصميم يؤثر بشكل عظيم على حياة الناس،
all lives.
كل الحيوات.
Design is a way in which we can feel included in the world,
التصميم هو الطريقة التي نشعر بها بالانتماء في هذا العالم،
but it is also a way in which we can uphold a person's dignity
لكنه أيضًا وسيلة تمكننا من دعم كرامة الشخص
and their human rights.
وحقوقهم الإنسانية.
Design can also inflict vulnerability
التصميم يمكنه أيضًا أن يلحق الضعف
on a group whose needs aren't considered.
على مجموعة تكون احتياجاتها غير معتبرة.
So today, I want your perceptions challenged.
لذا اليوم، أريد تحدي تصوراتكم.
Who are we not designing for?
من نحن الذين لم يُصمم لنا؟
How can we amplify their voices
كيف يمكننا أن نضخم أصواتهم
and their experiences?
وتجاربهم؟
What is the next step?
ما هي الخطوة التالية؟
Design is an enormous privilege,
التصميم هو امتياز ضخم،
but it is a bigger responsibility.
لكنه مسؤولية أكبر من ذلك.
I want you to open your eyes.
أريد منكم أن تفتحوا عيونكم.
Thank you so much.
شكرًا جزيلًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)